Praveen Kumar Thopalle

Praveen.thopalle@gmail.com | Ph: 682-716-8590 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/praveen-thopalle

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Skilled Software Engineer with proficiency as a SRE and in full-stack development. Expert in cloud services, Docker container orchestration, Kubernetes, and automating infrastructure with Ansible Playbooks. Unveiled ability to develop, deploy, and maintain highly available and scalable systems and services, with a strong prominence on automation and operational efficiency.

SKILLS

Languages: Python, Java, Typescript, JavaScript, PHP, Bash, Groovy.

Cloud Services: AWS (EC2, VPC, S3, ELK, EBS, CloudWatch, Route 53, Serverless Lambda, cloud

Formation, SNS, SQS, KMS, IAM etc.)

Orchestration Tools: Docker, Kubernetes, OpenShift, Ansible, AWS CloudFormation, Jenkins.

Monitoring Tools: Prometheus, Datadog, ELK, Splunk, Nagios.

On-premises Services: VM ware (VMware Hypervisor, vSphere, Tanzu, VMware Load Balancing etc.)

Databases: PostgreSQL, Oracle, MySQL, SQLite, Redis, AWS RDS, MongoDB, Cassandra.

EXPERIENCE

Dell EMC Inc.Senior Software Engineer

Santa Clara, CA Jan 2022 – Present

- Developed Automation tool to merge the GitHub PR's using GraphQL quires and eliminated 100% interventions to merge PR to development and production environments.
- Worked extensively on docker orchestration inside K8 clusters and allocated Jenkin agent resources by spin up pods for development and release branches builds improving VM horizontal scaling.
- Orchestrated the integration of Grafana widgets with Kafka topics, generating robust visual reports th
 at are now employed by over 100 users across analytics teams, driving a collaborative approach to
 data interpretation and strategy.
- Managed Kafka topic producer and consumer logs by implementing Argo CD and Red Panda pipelines enhancing system traceability and application efficiency by 40%.
- Utilized Prometheus for monitoring application alerts (reducing alerting noise by 25%), ensuring system reliability and scalability.
- Designed Ansible playbooks to streamline the orchestration of multi-tier applications, ensuring consistent configurations and simplifying the management of updates and patches for end-to-end automation with fully self-healing.

Samsung Semiconductors, Inc.

Senior Engineer

San Jose, CA *Aug* 2019 – *Dec* 2021

- Led Team in building REST API's and supported database setup for machine learning and deep learning models and deployed application though AWS EBS to achieved 0% downtime and allocating autoscaling resources across regions.
- Launched spot instances using spot fleet, achieving \$2k/year cost savings for cloud services, developing and deployment front-end microservice.
- Configured CUDA libraries to use GPU Resources for deep learning models on EC2 instances.
- Built CI/CD pipelines, automating microservice deployments with Docker and Kubernetes avoiding 100% manual deployment interruptions.
- Designed cron scripts in Bash for data ingestion for labeling archived last 10 years of data from public APIs for machine learning model training to accurately predict the Input data.
- Engineered comprehensive infrastructure as code (IaC) solutions using AWS CloudFormation, considerably reducing manual setup times and realizing more consistent environment deployments.

Indianapolis, IN Apr 2018 – Aug 2019

- Architect data ingestion and massaged more than 10Million records of data from oracle Golden gate to Elasticsearch using AWS Kinesis data streams for quick search completions across the application.
- Integrated auto suggests search queries using Elasticsearch and NodeJS as a backend Platform and deployed applications through serverless Lambda's and achieved search reaction time on entire application by 90%.
- Orchestrated SNS service Queue, and Published notifications through consumers for saved searches on 1million records users.
- Fully automated self-healing microservice using ansible playbooks in production environment, by alert notifications from Kibana logs and Improved application disaster latency by 85%.

Education

Master's - University of central Missouri, MI

Aug 2016 - Dec 2017

- Major Computer Information Systems.
- Field of expertise Enterprise Technologies.